[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
all right welcome everyone uh
to the stoa i'm peter limberg the
steward of the stoa
and the stoa is a place for us to cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the knife's edge
of this very moment and i actually had
some bad news or some sad news um to
start us off with
uh james carson's step daughter emailed
me this morning and he
passed away last night um james
was the author of finite infinite games
he was a friend of the stoa
he was even going to be a sense maker in
residence in november
but i'm told he did so uh in his home
that he loved with the woman that he
loved
and he was a wonderful human being so
may he rest in peace
and in his spirit let us continue to
play the infinite game here
at the stoa um today we have a very
special guest we have miriam mason
martinu
i hope i'm pronouncing her last name
correctly um
she's a therapeutic counselor and a
parenting coach she's a vice president
of
next step integral uh and she's a writer
author
um and she wrote a chapter in this
wonderful book cohering the integral
we space and
as you know the the regulation here at
the stoa the slow is becoming sort of
this informal hub of all these
conversational
uh conversational and interest objective
modalities we're inviting practitioners
in or practicing ourselves
uh getting a kind of a sense in
capacities to enter into these uh
deeply uh uh cohering spaces
uh so today is gonna be kind of cool
because we're gonna talk to uh miriam
about uh not so much her experience with
the spaces but sort of the inner work
required
in order to get into them um
so that being said how it's going to
work today it's going to be uh
me and miriam going to have a chat for
about you know 10 20 minutes
uh any time start throwing your
questions in the chat put q in front of
it
i'll call on you and meet yourself ask
it ask your question to miriam and then
um if you don't want to be on youtube
because this will be on youtube just
indicate that and i'll read it on your
behalf
um and there's something i want to
experiment today is the first time
i was just taking richard bartlett's
course and then they have all these like
as in spiral course and they have all
these kind of like hand gestures you do
like these resident fingers and stuff
like that i don't i don't want to do
that but there's something he said he
did like to
wrap up a question someone was going on
on a question just the facilitator does
this
uh in a very gentle way and this is not
to say that the question is bad or
anything it's just to kind of
indicate gently that to make room for
someone else to
make a question make a statement and to
land it so i will do this hopefully i
won't have to but i will do this if
someone is um going on with their
question and then
i will eventually uh jump in um so that
being said
miriam welcome to the stoa you're
allowed to unmute yourself now
thank you i'm delighted to be here with
you all
[Music]
so yeah maybe um we can get some
background uh like some
kind of context of uh how you came into
uh the work that you're doing right now
it goes way back um i was just telling
my daughter actually she's 17 now but my
husband and i met
in 1990 and that was before email or
before we were using email and
so we were writing letters for two years
i was in switzerland he was in canada
and a lot of our letter writing was
actually about community and how we need
to come together as a human family and
this is what's stopping the evolution of
humanity
so it kind of started i think really
through our
coming together um as a couple and
becoming fellow researchers and
inquirers into this topic
and living in community then for 10
years and doing a lot of experimentation
of what does it take
to come together in community
or in comunitas where you don't lose
yourself
because we've seen that happen and it's
not good
but also where you don't just reside in
the separate self
for all eternity and never actually
evolve what's possible as a collective
so that was really the driving inquiry
um
for that decade and then beyond we tried
it in many different
formats retreats seminars
living together with people and just our
own ongoing study and inquiry in the
topic
and then my therapeutic work is much
more one on one and working with couples
but it actually
informs the questions hugely because
it's all about what does it take
for us humans to show up
in a way beyond all the the labels we
put on ourselves what does it take for
us to show up for who we truly are
and um that is beyond our biography
and allow our actual authentic essence
to express itself more fully than ever
and yet be present to one another
without all these barriers of
separateness
um so that we can actually give rise to
something that's much more in our midst
i think that's really been our our focus
is how can we
how can we give voice to that which
arises when we come together
that is actually more than the sum total
of us and
in our decade of community living we
happened i i think a lot of it was grace
but we happened to
stumble upon some really profound
collective experiences of that nature
right at the start and then we got very
curious in unpacking
what are the what's the recipe what are
the ingredients so that this
is not just a state because i think even
even to this day
we can experience these deep states of
togetherness
and um and collective intelligence
collective wisdom we can experience
these as
momentary glimpses and tastes
we we have a pretty good read i feel now
on what is conducive you know and in my
experience making music together is a
really good inn
um celebration dance coming together i
was just at a
friend's wake on sunday and when you
come together with others around things
that matter
and that remind you of the actual
context of life
that often really brings a much deeper
shared field
in our midst and also when daily life's
challenges and not as present that's why
retreats and seminars and
and you know i've never been to burning
man i hear it works there too
um those kind of events can really allow
us to get a taste of what's possible in
our collective evolution
but then in daily life we seem to trip
up a lot
and and i feel like we've made so much
headway in our individual
journeys um but there's still a
there's still a real ceiling there as
far as our
latent potential um being able to
to come to fruition in the collective
and my husband and i are really of the
mind that it is the key to making um
making it through into a future that is
sane and sustainable for all
yeah i like that a couple things were
coming to mind is the
you know the what ken wilker talks about
uh from making a state to a trait
uh and how practice is needed for that
essentially
and the other thing that came was uh
soryu farrell's uh who's uh
head at the monastic academy when he was
talking about circling
uh he kind of threw shade at it and he
basically said that uh
circling is um intimacy without
friendship
it's like kind of get the the various
multitude of intimacy but you don't have
any commitment beyond that
and in order to make this kind of state
into a trait you need some kind of
structural commitments or calls your
practices and stuff like that
um yeah any thoughts on anything
i just said right there well i i totally
agree
that um you know i would never negate
those moments of intimacy because i feel
like their doorways their windows into
what's possible
and and i think they fulfill our deepest
yearnings
in a moment and so it's it's like you
kind of get lifted up to the top of the
mountain and you get to see the view
um but then you come back down and you
actually have to walk up
that path up the mountain and and you'll
have
moments when you're doubting yourself
and where you know get stormy et cetera
et cetera
so back to the the question of
how can comunitas how can that
collective being together and giving
rise to something
in our midst that is more than the sum
total of us and that has a voice
and that has intention and a will and
that we could potentially
receive guidance from for moving
forwards
um as a humanity like what does it take
in us to be present
to that in daily life and i think that's
a bit maybe the topic we could explore
today of you know it
it it is practice it's like working
muscles in us and what are those muscles
so i'd be happy to go in that direction
if that feels interesting to
all of you yeah um before we go on that
thread um
i just double click on the word
communitas or communitas um
uh we have we have like this uh we're
launching a communitas club here
the store we're exploring all these
interest objective practices and stuff
and we're out uh um mary um margaret
who's in the
uh audience today me and her gonna run
it we're debating we should call it that
because it's kind of like a mongrel
concept at least how i use it you know
it's like it means
many different things um and i guess the
distinction i have sort of like it's
like i
it type of way of relating versus an i
thou relating also relating for its own
sake it's like practices or a state that
a lot affords that
um i'm just curious how how do you hold
that term
i know i'm the one that suggested it for
the title as well but uh
how's that line for you well i i like it
so you
you sent it to me by email i've heard my
good friend jamie will uses it a lot um
i like it because i find the word
community is is
has been used and used and overused and
it has a lot of associations for people
that kind of
either just throw them off or actually
guide them down the wrong imagination of
what
what how we could evolve that so i i
i i stay away from community i often
talk more about village
or we practices or togetherness um
and i love communities actually went and
looked up a definition
that i could find after you sent me the
email
and it resonated beautifully it was um
coming together in intimacy right
in liminality so right at that threshold
of the unknown
and i thought that was very telling for
what we're exploring because i think one
of the
skill sets is actually to become quite
familiar and maybe even comfortable with
being at the edge of the unknown
together so i i think it's a great word
i like it
i love how you phrase that um okay so
the inner work needed to get into this
delicious state
uh what do you think okay
well i'll stop by saying i think it's an
ongoing journey
it's never done um
that um in in the way i frame it it
really
includes both our vertical
maturation and growth and development as
well as horizontal capacities and i can
get more into what i mean by that
um but with the vertical it's really
about
growing in our consciousness growing in
in the journey of awakening
getting to know remembering who we truly
are
um so practices of stillness of
meditation
of
really daring to remember
that under all the shoulds and
shouldn'ts and
thoughts and beliefs um
yeah all those those sticky notes that
we put on ourselves and that
other others put on ourselves there is a
core you that was there from the moment
you arrived and that doesn't actually
need to be developed or constructed that
is just there is already whole
so to remember that wholeness um or that
coming home to yourself i feel like
that's a huge one and then
and then getting skilled at knowing when
you're
entering any conversation any
relationship
any um yeah any relationship
which self are you coming from are you
actually coming from that home
within or are you coming from the
constructed more outside self
um that you have built in an effort to
manage and function and make do in this
world where once we realize when we're
about
one and a half two that were actually
separate in many ways from our mom and
dad and siblings and those
around us it can get pretty scary and so
we start patching together a
constructed self um but
yeah so that's one piece is that the
vertical which i think is it's it's an
evolutionary arc we're all on and we're
at different places in that
and each place has its purpose and it's
not at all
to make the ego self or you construct
itself bad i actually think that's a
real mistake
i think it's much more to be in right
relationship to it so to
to think of it more as that were a lot
of us anyways are still um
under the spell of a mistaken identity
and it's much more to write the
relationship
to that outside constructed self rather
than
to feel like it shouldn't exist or it's
a bad thing or it's the thing that's
keeping me from my spiritual growth
um i actually think if we didn't have it
wouldn't even be here in these
in these physical bodies um
so so yeah that that is a
big part of it though is remembering who
you are and being willing having the
courage to
when we come together with others to
actually bring that forth
and that can feel unknown too and
sometimes the path to it can feel quite
overgrown
so there's a practice there of like what
works for each of us might be different
to rediscover that
and you know often say to people what is
it that
what is it that helps you feel truly
most alive you know and it'll be
different things for different people
some it will be like having the most
intense conversation where
they're so in it that in a way they
forget themselves and
but they feel more themselves than ever
before and for another person it might
be when they just have those moments of
dancing
without any self-concern or lying
on on the ground and just breathing
deeply
or i though the ways there are
as many as there are humans on the
planet so
i think it's much more to find out what
works for you
when do you feel most alive
most you without trying to be you
um when do you feel most at home and can
you start discerning within yourself
between when you're in a way there and
when you're not
um and i think there's many many
spiritual practices and paths that have
been
discovered and shared and taught about
so i won't go into much more detail on
that for now
i'd like to also look at the horizontal
capacities because
in my experience and those are kind of
like a big embrace like a big embrace to
self and humanity right one is sort of
growing up the others growing out
and can we make that circle of care and
concern and love
wider and um and fuller both to
ourselves and to others and
a question that's been very alive for me
in this quest and i'd say even more as
i've gotten older is
is uh can we not just be intelligent and
articulate and conscious and spiritual
can we actually just be basically decent
human beings and that's kind of what i
mean with the horizontal it's like what
what does it mean to show up as a decent
human being
and then i'll often add how can we be
decent under duress because it's one
thing to show up decent when the sun's
shining and
um all is well but how can we really
draw upon
qualities and values and ethics that
make a life well-lived when the going
gets hard
and you know so those would be practices
of generosity practices of integrity
of um of respect
of treating one another no matter
age gender culture race
what have you no matter anything just
treating one another with respect and
with dignity and with
integrity and i you know because my work
is so often with
parents it that that comes up a lot with
little ones like how can we treat
the little ones with all the respect in
the world with all the integrity and
dignity no matter their
age but you could say the same about our
elders and about
really any human being i think if we
could just get that one right
we could solve so so many um of the
challenges we're facing
now that just seem to be getting more
extreme so
on it on a daily life do you want to say
something peter
or should i just keep going i'm enjoying
this
okay um in in daily life to me it's like
it's working both those muscle sets it's
like
how can i keep um
how can in a way let's let's just talk
about that that or remembering who you
are
how can i remember who i am but also
work with the ego self
like that which which um
[Music]
that which we build when we realize how
fragile how tender the human being
actually is like we have such thin skin
i'm always amazed like that
we survived some of us survived like my
grandma became 100 and died last year
like she made it until then like it's an
absolute miracle
when you think how fragile we really are
like it just takes a stick to poke at
you and you've already got a dent in you
um but then also psychologically and and
emotionally
we are fragile beings um and yet we also
can
claim and grow such sturdiness and
resilience
so a question that i really think about
in in the in the sense of those
horizontal skills is how can you
grow a an ego coat so it's
lightweight so it's like a lightweight
coat rather than
clunky armor knowing that yes we have
these
tender selves that when the going gets
rough when it's stormy outside we need
some protection so we build that outside
self
but can it be a coat that you know has
pockets that has things in it but
doesn't get
completely bogged down with massive
amounts of fear
um and trauma and defense mechanisms and
reactions so
a lot of the work is to see where that
coat has gotten clunky and has become
like armor and
to do the shadow work do the trauma work
do the um self-awareness work of
who am i what are my tendencies what's
my type where do i tend to trip up
um how can i work in a complementary
fashion with others rather than in a
rivalrous one and and bringing
those horizontal and vertical skill sets
together really is
i often talk about it as as if you think
of us like
all like instruments you know one of you
might be a violin one a cello one a
flute one a guitar etc
um if you think about the the work of
coming together to give
rise to what's in our midst
then it's a bit like if you wanted to
play music with others
whether that's a duet or a trio or in a
band or an orchestra
if you were a musician which i'm sure
some of you are
you would never stop playing music
together without first tuning your
instrument you just wouldn't and once
you stop playing
if you would notice by listening by
self-awareness right by being attuned by
listening that you're out of tune
you wouldn't continue you would actually
you know you see
you see especially the violent lin
players like they'll quickly do quick
tuning
um you so you would stop and then you
would re-tune and then you'd play a game
and i i use this better for a lot when
working with couples because i mean
couples will just jam themselves into um
talking about something and get
completely out of tune or start out a
tune
and be expecting to play music so
there's something there about once we
are working on our horizontal uh
horizontal and vertical capacities and
really integrating them so you know i do
come from a a very
integral perspective on life it's always
resonated deeply with
with the way i experience life is is to
grow in depth and width
um so to to hold both the psychological
and the spiritual
and the physical ending and the social
and all these aspects
um that they all are part of
us becoming well-tuned instruments and
knowing that we float in and out of
being in tune and out
of tune and that's completely fine so
another horizontal
capacity is to meet and greet ourselves
and others with kindness and compassion
and forgiveness you know it's something
i often say to my clients is
can we just go at this as if we're
pre-forgiven
you know because because ultimately i
think we are
so can we actually go at
this with a vulnerability and a courage
and a resilience
understanding that because we're humans
it's already for sure that we're gonna
make mistakes and trip
up and fall flat on our faces so if we
can just
assume we're pre-forgiven it can
actually allow us to take risks
and to um to in a way do the challenging
work of waking up
and and growing up but within a
i guess it's almost like within an
already embraced like within a vessel of
you already loved you already seen you
already heard
um because the i have just seen too
many times uh the efforts at
community village making um
you know or or the retreats and the
seminars where you're attempting to do
that i've
i've seen so many excellent aspirations
and good intentions
and deep thoughtfulness and great theory
around
this topic and before people
can even blink something can come from
who knows where
some shadow some trauma um
some deep hurt that just pops up and can
literally just
destroy the whole effort so to to
to not fool ourselves like we really
have to pay attention to
our psychological wellness
as much as our spiritual integrity
and uh and so i guess i want to
emphasize that in this conversation
so ask one more question uh start
putting your questions in the chat and i
will call
you in a moment so what was coming to
mind um
so this place is called stala and no
one's a stoic here except me basically
so i'm practicing stoic and one thing i
find with doing the stoic algorithm
um engenders what i call a para egoic
state rather than like a trans egoic
state like some of the buddhist
traditions are
non-egoic where you feel your ego it's
right here but it's like on the side and
you can still operate and be effective
in the world
um without it kind of like overcoming
you and co-opting
your behavior but if you just stay there
you you know you can become a sociopath
and i think a lot of people who have
trauma just
become stoic in that sense um without
any of that inner work uh
but i also like a most orthodox
christian eastern tradition
and they have a beautiful practice
called the jesus prayer and essentially
like you say
lord jesus christ son of god have mercy
on me a sinner and you focus
on the words coming out and then you
kind of while still focusing on the
words you focus on your mind
and then you focus on your heart then
you drop your mind to your heart then
you focus on all three at the same time
and it really has a somatic effect and
then you just basically unify them
uh what they what they call theosis um
so that's what i get from the horizontal
practice that you're referring to
so i'm wondering um is there any kind of
like go-to practices you you recommend
in order to have kind of like a healthy
relationship with the ego and also have
that horizontal thing that like loving
kindness or whatever
or do you think it's like has to be a
bespoke journey towards
each one of those things for for each
people or each person
i think having now worked for
over two decades as a therapist and
and just you know been married for
longer than that
and and just being a human for even
um i i think what's key
is that we know the work is ongoing
that we understand that shadow is real
and we need to
find a way to uncover it and integrate
and transmute it
that trauma is real that in my view
there is no such thing as a
non-traumatized human
there's bigger larger deeper fuller ones
um and there are little jolts to
sensitive nervous systems
um you know so and then there's
everything in between
um we all come with tendencies
uh we all have a typology so getting to
know that is a really excellent
practice like just get to know yourself
know what are your likely
stumbling blocks what are your likely
brilliances
that kind of thing um
finding a way to connect with the
biggest context
possible is is another key piece
and for some that could be devotional
prayer for another it could be
meditation for another it could be a
contemplation on death
um for another it could be being present
at birth
or just simply vulnerability can really
open up a door or beauty for me beauty
is huge as far as context
setting um so but
so so the way the way to for others it's
reading philosophical texts
but the the the way to that larger
context of like it
you know it's it's the remembering of
what actually
matters and it's not that it all needs
to be big
and huge and fancy because what matters
can happen in the stillness between you
and another or you and a dandelion
so um
[Music]
the the practice
within oneself of
it's like building a sturdiness or
resilience so
i'm all for heist i am i have a lot of
sensitivity as
i know that feeling like my skin feels
thin in this world and i find it quite
intense to be a human being
on this planet and the outside affects
me greatly and i think my insight
you know comes out quite easily um so a
a practice around this whole how do you
become a decent human being that has
really
worked for me is to build sturdiness
to build resilience so rather than to
then shut down because we feel so much
or because feeling so much is actually
part and parcel of
being fully human rather than to create
gates and walls around that
can we actually grow a sturdiness from
within
and that then really touches on skills
like
getting to know your nervous system know
how you can regulate
what suits you what are your main top
three to five triggers the ones that
just you know my
definition of a trigger is that which
when it hits you makes all your personal
growth and all your spiritual
aspirations flow out the
window at a second's notice that would
be a trigger so
if you can identify those and usually
triggers underneath them have unmet
needs and so once you know what the
trigger are you can
follow the tap route down find out
what's the need under it that's not
being met
which then really is a beautiful
diagnostic tool to find
out now how can i soothe that when that
trigger comes what do i actually need to
do to address it
to allow myself to regulate so um
in a way it's getting together i guess
like a toolkit that is both
um it's it's psychos virtual and then i
would
obviously include the body in it too so
we don't need to go in that i think
that's the topic that has become
widespread now which is awesome but you
know what do we feed our bodies what do
we feed our minds what we feed our
hearts and souls all of that counts
[Music]
i do think there's some very specific
practices that are
are key when we want to lean into
the unknown together as much as possible
from our authentic selves and one is
that
intrapersonal so it's the discernment
within myself
of when am i residing more in that
constructed
outside social ego self
and when am i resting
home in literally in my soul in my
essence and to start knowing that
difference and even feeling it
somatically like we
i always find it's funny how we theorize
about these things but
it really lives in the body like how
does my body feel
when i'm um residing home
and and i've noticed a lot with my
clients is just vocally so i'm a singer
on the side and and so i pay a lot of
attention to voice and
i've noticed sometimes when my clients
come in when they're not
centered when they're not grounded when
it's like they're out of tune when
they're off
their voices are a lot higher uh there's
like a frenetic kind of energy and
during the session you'll often
the voice will will come down it'll
start resting deep down in the chest um
it's like even the voice comes home how
does it feel in your chest
when you're home versus not so picking
up and getting really curious about any
of those clues that help you discern
which self am i bringing forward in any
moment and like you said
peter it's not about getting rid of the
ego it's about
having right relationship with it so
that when it matters
you can lay it it's like you can just
gently put it to the side and say okay
you sit here like a little cat
and i'm going to work here on bringing
forward my
authentic me into the circle because
in all our study of this topic stefan my
husband and i that
the the the key to coming together
without
losing self and actually becoming more
yourself than
ever before so where distinction is is
maintained but separation is dissolved
the key to that is our authentic self
like when we're really home in
who we are like that identity beyond
biography
that is the key to showing up in an
unrivalrous
all considerate sovereign fashion that
is it
in my experience
yeah i love that um okay so we're gonna
pivot to
questions
cool there's some so much good ones uh
let's go with steve you had a question
stefan uh steve henry about the
urgency of communitas
okay um i feel a sense of urgency that
this is needed
right away and yet it
seems like what is that this takes time
this kind of development
and so i'm wondering how
you cope with the sense of urgency
versus the time that's needed
first um your heart your questions
touches my heart like i almost have
tears when i hear it because i live with
this question every single day
and i couldn't agree with you more i
think you know the funny thing is i've
been feeling
the urgency since my twenties and i'm
now in my early
i'm 51 and so it's been it feels like a
long haul of feeling the urgency and i
think
i'm gonna borrow some of my my husband
stefan's
theories around this because you know
having lived with him
um it would be beautiful actually if he
was here i think he has felt
this urgency since the day he was born
so i just want to say i i
so get that feeling and i think the way
the world's going right now
it's it is becoming more and more i'd
say important i'm
maybe going to move away from the word
urgent but pressing and important
that we can break through like i i
literally
feel like the future of humanity is
dependent on it
so and at the same time like you said
yeah this is a long journey
however so partly i'm talking about
skills we can acquire partly i'm talking
about a journey of maturity so
there are i think more and more people
who have the capacity for what we're
talking about
i still think we have sometimes one side
in this like there's people with a lot
of horizontal capacities
and but who haven't maybe developed so
much of their vertical
um and and the other way around
at this point i'd almost sometimes
prefer working with the horizontal
elegant people um like to have
truly decent people because i feel like
the possibility of
coming home to self is is already
always there like we tend to make that
path very far in the future you know
it's like oh it's at least over
on the other continent but in my
experience it's at least as a state it's
the tiniest little shift within myself
like it's accessible at all times and
i can't tell you how many times in in my
uh in my
therapy sessions i'll i'll do i'll ask a
question i'll literally say
can you locate in yourself as a state
that home within where no matter what's
going on
no matter what you're completely and
naturally okay
completely and naturally loved
completely seen and free and heard
and alive and vibrant can you find that
state within yourself
and usually within a matter of seconds
every client i've worked can find it
it's not far away
so when the container is safe when
uh the relationship the foundation of a
relationship feels like something you
can
you can be vulnerable in and on
to to come home at least as a state
is not hard to stay there
is where it takes that knowing that
inner discernment the commitment the
will in a way the uh
the the remembering how important it is
to do that i think there are more and
more
people who have the horizontal
capacities i think the
that that coming home you can access
um and i actually you know i couldn't be
wrong on this
my husband and i could both be wrong on
this we talk about this a lot
i'd say over 90 of humanity if we
could break through to some kind of sane
existence
even if it's just a small collective
doing it at first
and start creating systems and
structures
from there over 90 of humanity would
easily happily glide into that
without having to do kind of the you
know creating the groove
like most people are just
wanting to live a good life and are
tired
of the rat race and this rivalrous thing
it doesn't mean we can't
all get rid of the rivalrous nature that
we are but there's i think there's
more and more people who feel like that
that arc has kind of done its time we're
literally destroying ourselves at this
point
um so i in that sense i have hope
however and here i'm going to borrow one
of the theories of my husband because he
he's
he's been hammering this for
into my my consciousness forever and
and it's that those of us who have the
incredible privilege
and the the the education and the time
on our hands
and the literally all the gifts and
blessings to be able to sit in this call
right now
rather than feeling like everyone else
just needs to catch up to us
what if we included that as a as a
consideration but
if we put our focus onto onto moving
forwards like moving beyond what we
already know
moving beyond what we're already
comfortable with moving beyond
like literally sitting right at the edge
of the unknown becoming familiar with
sitting in uncertainty together where
all we bring
totally humbly is literally like this
little offering bowl of here's my
authentic self
and i'm coming together with you and you
in you and now let's see what's possible
and can we get comfortable to sit in
stillness
until there's a nudge and impulse to
speak
through that little bowl um
you know so i i think i took a few
little loops there but
the the idea is yes it's urgent
thinking that we need to somehow get the
masses to this
place i don't think is realistic or
possible i think if we actually
um focused our focus
on moving that next it's kind of like a
next step but it often feels like a leap
because it's asking those of us who are
feeling that edge
to literally relinquish that which we
hold so dear and that we've practiced
and polished so much all our entire
lives which is highly sophisticated ego
cells that
can talk spiritual and look spiritual
and convince pretty much anyone else
that you're intelligent and a marvelous
human being and you you probably are
but can we actually let go of of even
the thinnest
veil that we're still holding and
literally come humbly
into the circle with others um
and if that gives any answers i'm
sitting in the inquiry with you so if
you have any thoughts i'm
very receptive
you have any uh follow-up thoughts or
questions steve
no
no i appreciate your answer thank you so
much
all right uh susan you had a question
um marion thanks for being here uh
great conversation um so
and it kind of just kind of i'm going to
wrap it up in what you just talked about
in terms of holding a safe space
for those who are willing and
and yet we run into and we deal with
people who
they're not aware of their own triggers
and of course
it's specific to when you talk about
trauma
they of course have a visceral reaction
um
how do you deal with that and especially
in light of yeah
is this is this a win-win or no deal
situation
so the setting
makes a big difference so in a
therapeutic setting that's one thing
when you're trying to um build
comunitats or
yeah or a village together that's
another thing and there's things you can
borrow
um you know one of my
central contemplations in the last few
years has been
what kind of culture do we need to build
so that we can be very elegant
with working with and through trauma
when it comes so it doesn't
trip up the incredibly important effort
of coming together
um and how can you do that and you know
i borrow insights here from
my work as a therapist which is
the rather than when trauma comes that
everyone freezes around i was like oh my
god
you know let's run the hills and the
whole thing falls apart which has
happened many many times
um rather than doing that and having
sort of a
mirrored freeze reaction from everyone
around in my experience
the the more i'll put it first with the
individual the more
an individual can can live into being
pre-forgiven
and can step into trauma work
in an even larger vessel of love so it's
like the bigger the love the more
possible to deal with trauma um
and we often think of love as something
on the other side or being connected
with self
or becoming unfrozen on the other side
of trauma
so a big part of what i'm um
thinking as far as a culture that can do
this elegantly
is can we marry what is often
um apart so can we
literally bring these incredibly
uh generous important capacities of
being pre-forgiven already loved
safety
[Music]
compassion the the notion that it's we
often talk about your ego my ego your
trauma my trauma what if we just put it
in the middle
and it wasn't so personalized because
that would also help with bringing down
some of the defense mechanisms
then it's just like oh trauma has
entered the space how are we going to
work with it rather than
susan's trauma just tripped us up or
miriam's trauma just did like
how can we actually just work with or
ego patterns oh an ego patron just
floated through what are we going to do
with it
you know we're just going to ignore it
sometimes ignoring is great are we
going to just see it are we going to
work with it
so one is to in a way depersonalize like
bring it into the middle
the other is to assure ourselves and one
another as a culture
that no matter what you are loved no
matter what i am loved
um because the times i have seen people
pull away when trauma happens is when
there is a lack
of there's a freakout basically there's
a lack of
connection and and feeling accepted and
and seen and heard and sheltered and
embraced through it all
and so there's a lot of shame then that
comes in an embarrassment and then
everyone
um goes apart rather than stays
turned towards each other to me it's
like can we create a culture where
we don't get bogged down by this because
it can also become an
endless endless journey of just uh
psychological work
can we keep the the direction of
where we need to head as a human family
sort of right at the four of our minds
and
and focus but when something comes
can we have the skill to work with it
um i guess elegantly really like
efficiently
lovingly uh
where there's a there's an awareness for
these things for one thing so they can
be named
and there's a clear understanding of
what we do when it happens ahead of time
um and that we do it in a way that
doesn't add in the secondary burdens of
shame and embarrassment
uh i think that's really a huge piece
so those those are some of my thoughts
i'm you know i'm working on this a lot
in my writing it's like
how can we create a culture of ethics
and
um and agreements that is conducive
to this kind of work happening where we
don't get tripped up because
like i said i've just seen too many
great efforts
sadly really just fall apart and i think
the time now more than ever
is that we are smart about how we go
about this and so we know where the
pitfalls are and we're prepared
to work with them um
yeah so i always say make the vessel
like it sounds maybe simplistic but when
you really put it into practice it it's
it's
it's quite incredible can you can you
always make love bigger than everything
else
like if you're having a conflict with
your partner okay the conflict's there
you get the information from it you try
and tune in can you just
just for a moment expand the context
make the love even bigger and ask
yourself what would love do in this
moment
and it might do something astonishing
like now's not a good time to talk
let's revisit this or i really need to
take a week just to consider something
or you know it doesn't always mean
diving in and being
soft and warm it can actually mean also
what would love do can mean that i grow
my
ability within myself to be
uncomfortable
like can i can i can i develop a
capacity to handle
stress and regulate at the same time and
this
in this way stay in the conversation can
i grow resilience to stay in rather than
have to pull out
as soon as the going gets hard um
and this is where i think emotional
intelligence and wisdom are as important
as spiritual awakening
i actually put them all in the same pot
but you know if you're going to tease
them apart they're as important
and it's it's one of my favorite quotes
i have no idea who said it but it lives
on my fridge and it's like instead of
waiting for the storm to pass can we
learn to dance in the rain
this is in a way what i'm talking about
like can we stay
in the fire can we stay in the rain
being kind and compassionate and
forgiving
and loving enough so that we can keep
doing the work
in the rain rather than going okay
that's too much got to take a break
wait until the storm has passed
all right um maybe gray you had a
question
um yeah sorry i hope that my my mic is
working uh can everybody hear me okay
okay cool
um so my question was about um i hear
you talk about like this
um like trying to locate this like deep
down
place where everything's okay and you
feel at home um
and i was just wondering like i know
that you say that for like 90
of the people it's easy um but i find
that a lot of times
it's not super easy for me um and so
i wonder about uh what what your advice
would be for
people like me or other people who have
maybe more difficult backgrounds and
didn't
get like to develop that deep down home
feeling
before how we can maybe discover it for
the first time or
or dig under whatever is burying it to
get at that
yeah beautiful um i'd like to start by
just saying
and i think it kind of swam in your
words it's never too late
um i'm absolutely convinced of that
um we can always we can always find that
wholeness because it it is there it
might be very tucked under but it is
there
so um healing is always possible and
sometimes we have stories of
attachment that was insecure or that was
fought with anxiety
and difficulty that can make it much
harder because we do live in these
bodies right
and in this emotional body and physical
body and mental and spiritual so
there's uh i i hear you and i think um
this is where i sometimes have this
image of it's there for all of us that
your core self is is fully alive and
there but the
path to it can sometimes feel overgrown
like
you know almost like you got to get a
machete out the first time and kind of
cut your way through
and then over time the more you come
back there the path kind of gets made
and then it does become easier
so in those kind of situations i feel
like working one-on-one with someone who
is skilled
in both the psychological and the
spiritual realm
um and who is trauma informed and has a
background in attachment
and childhood development um
that that's what i would suggest um you
know that that i think
is is the way because it it's uh
it's a journey and for some of us
there's a quick easy access but you know
when i say clients find it
within seconds usually these are clients
i've been working with for quite a while
on
these topics we've been talking about so
i have to give some context to that also
yeah but to remember even sometimes i
think
change happens if we just start
imagining like that's why i think
imagination is such a beautiful thing
because if you can't imagine something
it's really hard to kind of step into
something new so just in in talking
about community tasks too i mean if
there's one thing all of us could be
doing is
use our creative intention and
imagination to keep imagining where
we're heading as a humanity
in its best version i actually think
that is
it's like parting some clouds so we can
actually start going there and see where
we're heading
um but on on the note of your question
is
even if you just begin with the smallest
little step
of can i can i just open the doors or
the windows of my imagination and just
imagine
that there is some
some me some some self in me
that is actually whole can i just even
just stop
just with that that might be a beginning
awesome thank you so much
elf you had a question
thanks miriam uh my question was trying
to
get around how do you support communitas
in kind of a government's role a lot of
times
when you deal with governance sometimes
you just want certain things to emerge
and not trying to overly design
logically ahead of times but obviously
without good governance a lot of
communities implode
and then i just was in israel traveling
a bunch of kibbutz's
and that was one of the patterns i
noticed was this rigidity of ideology
and they had to become flexible over
time so they were stuck to a
communist ideology for better or worse
and the environment forces
a shift and they looked at that as a
failure and i looked at that as kind of
oh you had to experiment and pivot
um but from their ideological view it
was a failure but anyway i'm just
curious
the governance role i mean you kind of
start to touch on it with a culture and
ethics i think it's related there but
um i actually like i i've left just
listening to you because i feel like
you've held
bits of the answer in what you were
saying um and maybe me just reflecting
back will
will make you notice that like
one of the answers i would give that i
heard in what you're saying is that
we think of governance in a as a dynamic
evolutionary
thing rather than that it's ever fixed
because
true governance is is in a way
is governing in relationship to actual
reality like reality like with a big r
and i think a lot of what happens with
governance is you come up with roles
and functions and it like you say it
gets sultified it gets very rigid
and as soon as it's gotten ridges it's
out of touch with what gave
rise to why this particular person held
this role or this function
so to include in in
any kind of governance going forward
evolution
like tucked right into its very fabric
the that it does need to pivot and turn
and stay ideally um
yeah in touch with reality on a daily
basis
is a huge thing so a it's dynamic by
nature
um the other piece that comes to mind
is that governance that i think would
work best
has a lot to do with right relationship
like
both right relationship with myself and
with others like what what is really
mine to do what's yours to do
you know having lived in community for
for 10 years we we realized very quickly
that consensus decision making was not a
governance tool that we wanted to employ
because it was a headache it you know it
can be a step along the way but you end
up sitting potentially in a circle for
many hours and feeling like
you know the sun's going down soon and
the garden really needs to get planted
and so we found that it made a lot more
sense
to um notice who whose is it
to hold the overview of say the garden
and then to empower that person and
whoever was
flocking around that person to then go
do and yes check in report back
get get feedback if needed but
to to to go with what's sometimes i
think the answers are actually
more simple than we think like we like
to make things incredibly complicated
uh and and i agree life is incredibly
complex but can we
kind of like feel the the full
complexity and then
and then look through it and go is there
actually a simplicity on the other side
there
and so that's another piece that comes
to mind
around governance is what is
natural what just makes sense some
people
just naturally have um
overview they they just naturally have
this
overview they're not necessarily skilled
in any little particular field
but they always have this meta
perspective on the whole
um so someone like that would be much
more suited
to project management or leadership
you know of the ship rather than a
particular room on the ship
and then you know this is i think
governance that we have not yet explored
but
i think at the the edge of what's
possible would be a whole other kind of
governance which
includes what i just said but it is the
coming together
in our humble authentic
selves that are unique and beautiful and
distinct from each other but
not in that rival or separate separate
way
coming together like that and in my
experience
there actually is an other that can
enter
the space and what if what if that other
that is made up
of the sum total of us gathered
and more what if that could actually be
the
ultimate governing
voice and we're in relationship to it
listening for what is each of ours to do
and because if if we could literally get
through that eye of the needle
like you know when you said comunitas
was uh was intimacy
right in that liminal space i have to
think of you theory like
you can get to the bottom of the u like
really get to like we
you've emptied emptied emptied and you
just don't know and then you start to
listen for what's emergent
well what if what if governance could be
listening for that
that which comes when we've come
together emptied to the bottom of the eu
and now we're listening
we're listening from the future like i
don't think
we've even begun to live what's possible
as far as governance i think we just
have some clues around
i my clues like it needs to be evolution
it needs to it needs to make sense as in
be natural but it needs to be able to
change at a moment's notice etc
thank you all right beautiful um
so we are at the hour um it's
probably wise to close out here um
miriam do you have any closing thoughts
for us or anything that came alive for
you uh throughout today's session
uh probably just my enjoyment of hanging
out with you all
um it's been just lovely and seeing a
few of the faces
and and uh and you holding the space
like this peter and the inquiry like i
feel
heartened really i feel heartened to
know that you all exist and that you
care
about this topic and that um
because it can feel so daunting so maybe
i just want to
gather my heartedness with hopefully
some of yours
and put it in the middle and just remind
us
all this is not a time to give up this
is a time
to keep at this like those of us who
feel
that this is important that you know are
broken and cracked open by what's going
on around the world
but um like just i guess i just want to
say let's all take heart
let's not give up uh we've got to do
this we really do like i
we start thinking about the future and
future generations and the children just
being born
it's like we can do this and it
and if we can remember that maybe it's
easier than we think
like not like hard but easy or let's say
maybe it's more simple than we think
even if it's hard but
i think we we have everything we need at
our fingertips
we really do we know we know what it is
like to be a decent human being
and and we all have had moments that we
remember
you know even if it's just a tiny
glimpse we remember who we are
yeah i love that and i especially found
this session awesome uh because what
you're coming in with
just not only with your essence your
presence
um but with what you're saying resonates
really well with what we've been doing
here
at the stoa for the last six months um
and there is sort of like maybe i'm
speaking on behalf of myself this
this within the store and then kind of
the buzz it's getting there's like a
boyish optimism
that we're going to like steal the
culture you know seduce the culture heal
the culture
and the trauma scene that we're in um
and it's fun
you know and it's exciting uh and
delicious um
so thank you so much for coming to
sloa today thank you thank you everyone
um so i'll close up with some
announcements we have a
few events today
the spiritual mission of america and the
anthropocene with matthew siegel
that's 6 30 pm eastern time you can rsvp
there
and then after that uh at
8 00 pm eastern time we have painting
with words loving transformation or
something with tim adeline from the
voice craft and he's doing
an interesting conversational practice i
have no idea it's gonna be like an art
performance i imagine uh
and then the election between biden and
trump is right after that so uh
you know you can buckle up uh with some
psychotech before you watch that
and then uh um the website
patreon sub stack uh yeah
that being said thank you everyone thank
you miriam
we'll close out with some music